in previous lessons we have seen that a
super scaler processor will try to
execute more than one instruction per
cycle viw processors are trying to
achieve the same amount of work per
cycle but in a different way so let's
compare the two approaches and see how
the vliw processors differ from the out
of order and in order supercal
processors that we have been already
seen so what we will do is compare the
outof order supercal processor the in
superill processor and a very long
instruction word or vliw processor
according to several things first how
many instructions per cycle do we try to
do an an issue out of for super skill
processor is trying to do up to n
instructions per cycle an in order
supercale procor is also trying to do up
to end instructions per cycle a vliw
processor is different in that it tries
to execute one large instruction per
cycle but that one large instruction
does the same work as n normal
instructions would do so really we're
trying to do the same work per cycle but
the super skill processors are trying to
do more than one simple instruction per
cycle whereas a v w processor does one
large instruction that really does the
same work as n of these but it needs to
be given a single instruction to do per
cycle in terms of how do we find
independent instructions that we can do
in a cycle the outof order supercal
processor Finds Its n instructions by
looking at much more than this number of
instructions in its instruction window
so it fetches the codes and then kind of
has a window of more than n instructions
and among these it's trying to find the
N that it needs to execute in contrast
an in order supercale op procor is
trying to execute up to n instructions
per cycle by looking at only the next n
instructions in program order so it
doesn't maintain this huge instruction
window among which it is trying to find
an instructions instead it just tries to
see whether the next n instructions or
some subset of them can be executed in
program order in parallel a vliw
processor doesn't even try to find
independent instructions it simply tries
to do the next large instruction so it
behaves like a non-s supercal processor
that executes instructions in order it's
just that each of these instructions is
really describing a lot of work in terms
of Hardware cost this looking at many
instructions in order to find the end
that we're looking for in an outof order
supercale processor is really expensive
the in order supercale processor does a
lot less work and needs a lot less
Hardware to find the instruction s so
it's less expensive in terms of Hardware
cost than their out of order supercal
cousins the vliw processor reduces that
cost even further so it's even less
expensive than an in order supercal
processor for the same amount of work
per cycle assuming we can find that work
because we are now even simpler in
finding that work and that brings us to
our last point which is does the
processor need help from the compiler in
an autof supercal processor it does
pretty well even without any compiler
help but the compiler can help improve
the program performance an in order
supercal processor is more dependent on
the compiler if the compiler doesn't do
anything to put independent instructions
consecutively then an in order supercal
processor will not have good performance
it's performance will lag significantly
the performance that an out of for the
processor with the same issue with would
be able to achieve so an in order
supercal processor really needs help
from the compiler without such help it
is going to perform significantly worse
than an aof for the processor would and
finally a VW processor completely
depends on the compiler to produce
performance if we don't have a good
compiler a vliw processor will fail
miserably as far as performance is
concerned so as we can see among this
three the autof super skll processor is
trying to do kind of like a hardware
intensive I don't need much help from
anybody but it sacrifices Hardware to do
that and in order super skill processor
tries to reduce the hardware cost but
still can execute the same program that
an outof for super skill processor could
and in some programs it really needs
compiler help in order to achieve good
performance and finally a vliw processor
goes to the extreme of completely
depending on the compiler to provide and
express the parallelism it needs to do
work but in exchange it gives us much
lower cost